Guide to the Edward Otho Cresap Ord Letters, 1854-1885
Department of Special Collections
- Correspondence, 1866 Oct. -1879 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 43. 1879, Sept. 9.San Antonio. To Wife. NP.
    Ned & Johnny up for exam, visitors, children, California Mission Mills all wool flannel.
  - 44. 1879, Sept. 13.San Antonio. To Reginald. NP.
    Jimmie and plans for raising, J. gone to Good Templars (temperance society). Frag., torn corner.
  - 45. 1879, Sept. 13.San Antonio. To Wife. [St. Albans?].
    Changes, Ned & Johnny still taking exam, Jimmie, Senator Genl. Maxey to visit, company.
  - 46. 1879, Sept. 16.San Antonio. To Molly. NP.
    Mail, Ned & Johnny passed, question of Regts. & postings, teacher -Capt. Coyt, home news.
  - 47. 1879, Sept. 19.San Antonio. To Molly. NP.
    Genl. & Mrs. Maxey, visit missions, personal, Jimmy's troubles, Bertie, etc.
  - 48. 1879, Sept. 26.San Antonio. To Wife. NP.
    Iron Mountain Train, family, mining excitement.
  - 49. 1879, Sept. [27], 28.[San Antonio]. To [Molly]. NP.
    San Francisco news, Grant -"it looks as if he would be our next President in spite of the politicians," Ned's appointment as 2nd Lt., also Johnny. Frag., pages 2 & 3 only.
  - 50. 1879, Sept. 29.San Antonio. To Wife. NP.
    Riding party, family.
  - 51. 1879, Sept. 31.[sic] San Antonio. To Wife. NP.
    Family, Dr. Ornelas, philosophy & faith, Mr. Custer, Mrs. Young, Genl. MacKenzic.
  - 52. 1879, Oct. 3.San Antonio. To Wife. NP.
    Family, Maj. Thornburg killed and 4th Cav. Going to area, rumors of war.
  - 53. 1879, Oct. 4-6.San Antonio. To Wife. NP.
    Mr. Custer (Lt.), family news.
  - 54. 1879., Oct. 8.[San Antonio]. To Molly. NP.
    Bertie & Lt. Custer, family news.
  - 55. 1879, Oct. 9.San Antonio. To Molly. NP.
    Personal, family news, Bertie and beans, memories of 25 year marriage, aging.
  - 56. 1879, Oct. 15.St. Louis. To Molly. NP.
    Chiding, lost luggage.
  - 57. 1879, Oct. 16.St. Louis. To [Molly]. NP.
    Personal, family.
  - 58. 1879, Nov. 17.San Antonio(?). To Lucy & John. NP.
    Local news, Mama home, advice.
  - 59. [187-. ND]. [prior to 1878].Palmer House, Chicago. To Lucy. NP.
    Lucy's school, Chicago & traffic, all family at home, Gen. Perry.
- Correspondence, 1880 -1885 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1. [1880-81?].[Washington, D.C.?]. To Molly (daughter). NP.
    Saved trouble of canvassing for votes, uncle in Florida, Col. Brown, Calif. friends and news, bill before Congress, Gen'l. Joe Johnson of Va., [Ord's retirement].
  - 2. 1881, Mar. 29.[Mexico?]. To Wife. NP.
    Plans for starting house delayed, cave, Gen. Trevino, Bertie going to Puebla, homesick, must stay until makes some money, city unhealthy, Tacubaya suburb, present.
  - 3. 1881, April 1-2.Puebla, Mexico. Bertie A. Trevino and E.O.C. Ord to Molly Ord. NP.
    Puebla sulphur baths, ulcer, miscarriages, at bishop's house -description, Tacubaya, "our petroleum company," different customs, American sight-seers, medicines, will be hard to convert to Catholicism, elegant houses, Puebla town. Fragile.
  - 4. 1881, April 4.Mexico. To [Molly?]. NP.
    To start back home, business. Fragile.
  - 5. 1881, April 9.Mexico. To Lucy. NP.
    Lucy's baby, Tacubaya, drills at military college, Gen. Grant, Chapultepec Castle, review and mock battle.
  - 6. 1881, April 13.Mexico. To Wife. NP.
    To go to Puebla on business, supper with Grants, memories, sham battle, petroleum company classes in Mexico, not much hope of success for an English school and description of mock battle. Marked pages 1-7.
  - 7. 1881, May 18.Vera Cruz. To Molly. NP.
    Business, Vera Cruz, Mr. Finley, Orizaba, Jimmie, onyx, railroad work available.
  - 8. 1881, Oct. [21].Mexico. To Lucy. NP.
    Family coming, winter climate, no fires. Frag.
  - 9. 1881, Nov. 5-6.Mexico. To [Jimmie]. NP.
    College marks, spelling, trip, Orizaba, sketch of waterfall, girls boarding schools, Mexican customs.
  - 10. 1881, Nov. 7.City of Mexico. To Lucy & John. NP.
    Arrival of Bertie and "Mama," railroad from Vera Cruz to Orizaba, seven carriages, Indians, trees and scenery, difficulties adjusting, Shafters.
  - 11. 1881, Dec. 25.Vera Cruz. To Lucy. Columbia, Ohio.
    Christmas letter, new port, Sherman, Grant, politics, note to Ruth from sister, Lucy.
  - 12. [1881. Dec.?].NP. To Ruth. NP.
    Personal, advice, Mrs. Genl. Mason.
  - 13. [1881-83?].[Mexico?]. To [Molly]. NP.
    Frag., bottom of page with signature.
  - 14. [1881-83?].[Mexico]. To [daughter]. [Washington, D.C.?].
    Family summer plans, Washington, Rawley, Front Royal, Garry. Frag., pages 5 6
  - 15. 1882, Jan. 16.Vera Cruz. To [Garesche]. NP.
    Journeys, Monterey, Jimmie at Laredo, Ned at Ft. Clark, John Mason at Ft. Davis.
  - 16. 1882, Feb. 22.City of Mexico. To Ruth. Brooklyn, N.Y. Doctors.
  - 17. 1882, May 2-18.City of Mexico. To Sister. NP.
    Inquires after [Marcy?], died.
  - 18. 1882, May 21.Mexico. To [Garesche?]. NP.
    Pleased with grades, last month with Water, Pierce & Co.
  - 19. 1882 Dec. 6.City of Mexico. To Ruth. NP.
    Family news, John W. Garratt.
  - 20. 1883, Jan. 30.Mexico. To Ruth. NP.
    Health doctor of Ladies Hospital, "guitar" lessons, family.
  - 21. 1883, April ?.Mexico. To Ruth. NP.
    Accident, mail instructions.
  - 22. 1883, Mar. 28.Mexico. Ruth & Molly. NP.
    Exposure to yellow fever in Vera Cruz, wants daughters to learn to operate telegraph. Frag.?
  - 23. [1883, June 19].Mexico. To [Mollie?]. NP.
    Hopes for raise. Fragile frag.
  - 24. 1883, July 2.Mexico. To Wife. NP.
    New company, personal. Frag.?
  - 25. [1883?].Mexico. To Wife. NP.
    Family, Gen. Escobedo, note to Lucy.
  - 26. [1883?].NP. AD. note of R.R route etc. to San Luis, S.T. Fuller, Laredo, Texas.
  - 27. 1884, Dec. 24.NP. Jay Gilly to Mrs. Ord. NP.
    ALS. re: offer of "Surrender Table".
  - 28. 1885, Jan. 30.New York. Cyrus W. Field to Mrs. Ord. Old Point Comfort, Va.
    ALS. & clipping re: buying "Surrender Table".
- Biographical material (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1. Reference note
  - 2. "Old Tooduts" Edward Otho Cresap Ord. 1818-1883, by Ord Mason. Unpublished typescript. 93 pages including photographs.